Guide to the Edward James Parrish papers, 1888-1926 and undated RL.00998
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Edward James Parrish papers
1888-1926 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Murai family
Parrish, Rosa Bryan
Parrish, Edward James, 1846-1920
Parrish, Lily Virginia
Kusakabe, Kinbē, 1841-1932
RL.00998
9.2 Linear Feet 31 boxes; 3 oversize folders; and 6 volumes Approximately 1500 items
Tobacco manufacturer, resident of Durham, North Carolina, and Tokyo, Japan. The papers of Edward James Parrish primarily consist of business and personal papers, correspondence (chiefly 1900-1921), and photographic collections of Parrish and of his wife, Rosa Bryan Parrish. Items include a notebook on tobacco trade in China and Japan (1894-1900), letter books (1900-1904), and a scrapbook created by their only daughter Lily Parrish. Turn-of-the-century photograph albums relate to the Parrishes time in Japan (circa 1899-1905) and form a large series of their own. Two were assembled by Kichibei Murai of the Murai Brothers, a Tokyo cigarette manufacturing company of which Parrish was the first vice-president; they contain photographs of his residences and of banks, mines, oil fields, farms and tobacco factories in which he had an interest. Also included are seven fine souvenir albums with large hand-tinted albumen prints from noted Japanese studios, including that of Kusakabe Kimbei. There are also personal photograph and postcard albums of the Parrish's travels in Japan, Korea, and China, and Mrs. Parrish's reminiscences and impressions of her life in Japan. Loose family photographs and portraits dating from about 1890 to 1920 round out the collection.
Access Restrictions
Original glass plate negatives are closed to use. Contact the Rubenstein Library for assistance with access to these images.
Provenance
The Edward James Parrish Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as gifts, purchases, and transfers from 1941 to 1987.
Biographical Note
Edward J. Parrish (1846-1920) and Rosa Bryan Parrish (1852-1927) were residents of Durham, North Carolina, and traveled to Japan and China in connection with Parrish's work as a representative for American Tobacco and the British-American Tobacco Company. During his successful operations in Japan establishing a tobacco market, Parrish had conferred upon him by the Emperor of Japan the "Third Order of Honor," and was decorated with the "Medal of Sacred Treasure."
Edward James Parrish was born in 1846 in the tiny community of Round Hill, in what was then Orange County, N.C. (now northern Durham County), son of D.C. Parrish. He attended Trinity College, and served for a short time in Company "K," 4th N.C. Cavalry, in the last year of the Civil War.
He married Rosa Bryan of Chatham County in 1870 and moved to the small post-Civil War railroad depot named Durham around 1871 to establish a grocery and confectionery store. He then became a tobacco auctioneer, and built the first brick tobacco warehouse in Durham in 1879 (later destroyed by fire). The Parrish family's primary home in Durham before moving to Japan in 1898 was a large Second Empire structure on Main and Dillard; upon his early retirement around 1904, he remodeled "Lochmoor," originally a farmhouse on North Roxboro Road (both residences were later demolished). Their only daughter, Lily, married Professor R. L. Flowers, of Trinity College.
Source: Ancestry.com; NCpedia; Durham-Orange-Wake County NcArchives Biographies, USGenWeb. A 1916 biography of Parrish, reproduced on the USGenWeb site, incorrectly states his birthplace as "Pound Hill."
Collection Overview
The Edward James Parrish Papers include business and personal correspondence (chiefly 1900-1921) of Parrish and of his wife, Rosa Bryan Parrish. There are also various bills, a notebook on tobacco trade in China and Japan (1894-1900), letter books (1900-1904), photographic collections, several postcard albums, and a scrapbook created by Lily Parrish.
The papers also include Rosa Parrish's reminiscences and impressions of her life in Japan, as well as her writings on the status of women. There are also materials relating to Kichibei Murai's family and to Murai Brothers Company in Japan, close partners and friends of the Parrish family.
Photographic formats include glass plate negatives, loose prints, photo postcards, and over 20 albums. Two of the photograph albums date from the late 19th century and were owned by Kichibei Murai; they contain photographs of his residences and of banks, mines, oil fields, farms and tobacco factories in which he had an interest. Also included are black-and-white late 19th and early 20th century loose albumen and early gelatin silver prints of family members.
The photograph albums document the Parrish family's travels in Japan, China, and Niagara Falls, and include personal snapshots taken at these locations as well as in their home of Durham, N.C.; there are also many commercial souvenir photographs from Japan. The latter take the form of large finely handtinted albumen prints of Japanese scenery, landscapes, cultural sites and temples, clothing, entertainment, and transportation, housed in high-quality souvenir photograph albums; many of these feature highly decorated lacquer inlay covers, elaborate bindings. Most include captions. The studio of Kusakabe Kimbei, a noted photographer, created many of the prints and albums, and the work of other notable studios have also been identified.
Related Material
Richard Henry Gregory papers, 1905-1910 (employee of British-American Tobacco in China)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James Augustus Thomas Papers, circa 1900-1985 (tobacco merchant involved in early trade with China)
Americans -- Japan; Cigarette industry -- East Asia; Cigarette industry -- Japan -- Tokyo; Industries -- North Carolina -- Durham; Photography -- Japan -- History -- 19th century; Tobacco industry -- North Carolina -- Durham; Tourism -- Japan -- History -- 19th century; China -- Description and travel; China -- Photographs; Durham (N.C.) -- History; Japan -- Description and travel; Japan -- Photographs; Albumen prints; Glass plate negatives; Letter books; Photographs; Photograph albums; Postcards; Scrapbooks; Parrish, Edward James, 1846-1920; Murai Kyodai Shokai, Tokyo; American Tobacco Company
- Correspondence, 1888-1927; 1
  Scope and Contents
  The correspondence contains primarily the business correspondence of Edward James Parrish regarding the controlling interest of the American Tobacco Company and its role in the Japanese tobacco firm, Murai Brothers Company. It details the day-to-day business as well as the settling of affairs upon the sale of the Murai Brothers Company to the Japanese government during its creation of a tobacco monopoly. There is a small amount of personal correspondence, mainly celebrating the fiftieth wedding anniversary of Mr. and Mrs. Parrish, as well as condolences sent upon Edward Parrish's death.
  Related materials can be found in the Volumes series, which contains E.J. Parrish's letterbooks with copies of his outgoing correspondence.
  - Business Correspondence, 1888-1919; 1
    - 1888-1902 (Box 1)
    - 1903 Jan-Feb (Box 1)
    - 1903 Mar (Box 1)
    - 1903 Apr-May (Box 1)
    - 1903 June-Dec (Box 1)
    - 1904 Jan-June (Box 1)
    - 1904 July-Aug (Box 1)
    - 1904 Sept-Dec (Box 1)
    - 1905 (Box 1)
    - 1915-1919 (Box 1)
    - 1899-1904 (Box 4)
      Scope and Contents note
      Oversize.
  - Personal Correspondence, 1909-1927; 2
    - 1909-1927 (Box 1)
    - 1900-1923 (Box 2)
      Correspondence of Mrs. Parrish.
  - Letter Books, 1900-1909
    Parrish's letter books with carbon copies of his outgoing correspondence, largely based in Durham, N.C., or Tokyo, Japan. These books contain many details about the state of the tobacco trade in Japan, lawsuits and patents regarding recipes and manufacturing procedures, the everyday business affairs of the Murai Brothers Company and the American Tobacco Company, as well as the steps taken to dissolve the Murai Brothers Company and American Tobacco Company's interest in it after Murai Brothers was purchased by the Japanese government.
    - Letter book, Durham, N.C. and Tokyo, Japan, 1900 Jan. 17-Sept. 25 (Volume L:5686)
    - Letter book, Durham, N.C. and Tokyo, Japan, 1900 Oct. 4-1901 Aug. 27 (Volume L:5687)
    - Letter book, Durham, N.C. and Tokyo, Japan, 1901, Aug. 28-1902 Aug. 4 (Volume F:5688)
    - Letter book, Durham, N.C. and Tokyo, Japan, 1902 June 24-1904 Oct. 18 (Volume L:5689)
    - Letter book, Durham, N.C. and Tokyo, Japan, 1902 Aug. 11-1903 Dec. 16 (Volume F:5690)
    - Letter book, 1903-1904 (Box 10)
      Volume measuring 10 x 13.75, re: Murai Bros. and American Tobacco.
    - Letter book, Durham, N.C. and Tokyo, Japan, 1904 Sept. 26-Dec. 2 (Volume L:5691)
    - Letter book, "Private," for Capt. E.J. Parrish, 1905-1907 (Box 29)
    - Letter book, 1909 (Box 30)
    - Letter book, "Private," for E.J. Parrish, 1907 Mar. 11-1909 Mar. 26 (Box 30)
- Legal Papers, Financial Documents, and Business Documents, 1899-1947; 2
  The bulk of this series comprises documents related to the Murai Brothers Company in Japan, and includes information on tobacco manufacture and purchase, details on the Japanese tobacco factories, and general business practices. There are also a few personal financial documents.
  - Legal Papers, 1899-1911; 3
    - 1899 Mar 25-1909 Jan (Box 2)
    - 1911 Mar 20-1928 (Box 2)
  - Financial Documents, 1900-1947; 4
    - Murai Brothers, 1900-1904, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Personal Financial Documents, 1908-1947 and undated (Box 2)
    - Bryan and Walker pocket ledger, undated (Box 30)
      Includes entries on Moore and Schlery accounts.
    - E.J. Parrish bank account book with Fidelity Bank, Durham, 1912-1915 (Box 30)
  - Business Documents, 1902-1903 and undated; 5
    - Notebook on Tobacco Trade with China and Japan, 1894-1900 (Box 9)
      Leather-bound volume, 6 x 9 inches, author unknown. Largely empty, but includes notes on sales, brands, and types of tobacco sold in Asia in the late nineteenth century.
    - Cigarette and Tobacco Manufacturing Procedures and Formulas, undated (Box 3)
    - Brief History of the Tobacco Tax in Japan, undated (Box 3)
      Manuscript.
    - Statements of Manufacturers, Murai Bros Co. Limited, Kyoto Factory, 1902 (Box 3)
    - The Informations Required, Tokyo Factory, undated (Box 3)
      Questionnaire with answers.
    - Tobacco Manufacture and Purchase, 1902 and undated (Box 3)
    - Osaka Gas Company, 1903 (Box 3)
    - Murai Brothers, undated (Box 3)
    - E.J. Parrish Lots with Prices, 1911 Aug. 4 (Box 3)
      Volume, measuring 8.5 x 13, with handwritten details about Parrish's lots and account settlements. Includes typescript index in the front of the volume.
    - Realty sale poster (Oversize-folder 1)
    - E.J. Parrish "Ledger No. 1" account book, 1900s (Box 29)
      Account book with real estate, farm, and lumber accounts. Includes Trinity College, Parrish Place, West Durham Land Co., as well as other Durham companies. Loose inserts, receipts, and account slips laid in. Also includes pedigree applications for different horses tipped into the front.
    - North East Land Company account book for E.J. Parrish real estate projects, 1917 (Box 29)
- Personal Documents, 1899-1921 and undated; 3
  Series contains certificates, travel documents, clippings, and various personal writings. Of particular interest is a piece by Rosa Parrish in which she details her impressions of Japan and Japanese culture, as well as fragments, presumably by Mrs. Parrish as well, that discuss the role of women and the advancement of their rights in government and society.
  - Ancient Free Masons Master Mason Certificate, 1899 February 27 (Box 3)
  - Certificates and travel documents, 1899 and undated (Box 3)
  - Clippings, 1900s and undated (Box 3)
  - Impressions of Japanese by Rosa Parrish, circa 1905-1920 (Box 3)
  - Personal receipts, 1920-1921 (Box 3)
  - Printed materials, 1905-1920 and undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous writings, undated (Box 3)
  - Parrish family coat of arms, undated (Box 4)
  - Parrish family genealogy, undated (Box 3)
  - Popular cook book, 1899 (Box 3)
    Incomplete copy. Missing several pages.
  - Recipe: "War Cake," undated (Box 3)
  - Writings (Japanese), undated (Box 3)
  - Writings on women's rights, 1900s (Box 3)
    Presumably those of Rosa Parrish.
  - Medal, undated (Box 12)
  - In Memoriam: Nannie Graham Carr, 1915 (Box 8)
    Bound volume printed in memory of Nannie Graham Carr (1838-1915), wife of industrialist Julian Carr of Durham.
  - Miscellaneous papers and notes relating to Sunday School (some on Lyon Company Tobacco letterhead), undated (Box 31)
- Photographs, 1883-early 1900s and undated; 4
  The images in this series chronicle the Parrish family and their time in Japan, and also document two of their Durham estates (both of which are no longer standing). Formats include albumen prins and early modern gelatin silver prints; there is also a series of glass plate negatives. There are family portraits as well as amateur snapshots.
  A number of the photographs are housed with the oversize material.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original glass plate negatives are closed to use. Please contact the Rubenstein Library for assistance with accessing these images.
  - Japanese portraits, undated (Box 3)
  - Family photographs, early 1900s and undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Portraits of E.J. Parrish, undated (Box 3)
  - Lochmoor estate, early 1900s (Box 3)
  - Old Wright home, 1883 and undated (Box 3)
    Includes clippings about history of the estate.
  - Parrish family portraits, undated (Box 4)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 4)
    Oversize photographs.
  - Glass plate negatives, circa 1899-1905; 18 photographs (Box 27)
    Set of 18 black-and-white images form part of a 38-item 4x5 inch glass plate negatives series, and depict the Parrish family in Japan, street scenes, and tourist sites such as temples. Caption list for 18 plates (incomplete) created by Mrs. Parrish on hotel stationery is included in the box.
  - Glass plate negatives, circa 1899-1905 (Box 28)
    Set of 20 black-and-white images form part of a 38-item 4x5 inch glass plate negatives series, and depict the Parrish family in Japan, street scenes, and tourist sites such as temples. Caption list for 18 plates (incomplete) created by Mrs. Parrish on hotel stationery is included in the other box of plates.
  - Original box for the glass plate negatives (Box 28)
    Sample of original box used to house the glass plate negatives. Includes signature of Mrs. E.J. Parrish.
  - Albums of pictures of Japanese houses, photos (Oversize-folder 2)
- Photograph Albums and Scrapbooks, 1890s-1910s
  Series comprises bound and disbound albums created and collected by the Parrish family largely during their time in Japan from about 1899 to 1905.
  Three of the photograph albums contain black-and-white photographs depicting the Japanese estates and staff of Kichibei Murai, of the Murai Brothers Company, and may have been given as a gift to the Parrishes as a souvenir of their stay, or assembled by the Parrish family from photographs they took or had taken.
  Seven of the albums are of the kind commercially produced and sold to tourists, and contain large hand-colored albumen photographs taken by well-known Japanese photographers of the time. The traditional tourist scenes feature city views, mountain and coastal landscapes, parks with lotus ponds and cherry blossoms, cultural and historic sites, agricultural and business enterprises, and portraits of Japanese men and women in native dress, including rickshaw owners, geishas, artisans, farmers, children, and wrestlers. Many of these albums were probably assembled from photographic prints chosen by the Parrishes, but some may have been pre-assembled by the studio.
  The Parrish family's personal photograph albums include black-and-white snapshots and formal portraits taken by family members and friends during the family's travels to Japan, North Carolina, Niagara Falls, and other unidentified places. There are also a few large-format colorized photographs.
  A scrapbook rounds out the collection of albums, and was contains calling cards and other memorabilia related to Lilly Parrish (d. 1948), the wife of President Flowers of Duke and only daughter of Edward James and Rosa Parrish.
  - Lily Parrish scrapbook, circa 1890-1910 (Box 5)
    This scrapbook measuring 8 x 11 inches was originally titled "Scrapbook of Mrs. E. J. Parrish," but may have been assembled by her daughter Lilly as it contains Miss Parrish's calling cards, notes, clippings, memorabilia, and collected souvenirs. Handwritten notes and captions are occasionally included.
  - Kichibei Murai postcard album, 1898-1900 (Box 7)
    Souvenir volume labeled Postkarten Album 1915, 8 1/2 x 10 1/4 inches holds captioned postcards of Japan and Korea, including office buildings, street scenes, coal mines, and other scenery.
  - Photograph album with scenes of Kichibei Murai's house and grounds, circa 1899-1905 (Box 6)
    Cloth-covered volume bound accordion-style, measures 6 1/2 x 8 1/4 inches, and includes albumen photographs of Kichibei Murai's home and grounds in Tokyo, Oiso, and Kyoto. Some loose prints are inserted in the back of the volume. May have been given by Murai as a gift to the Parrish family in remembrance of their stay in Japan. It is also possible the Parrish family took the pictures and assembled the album.
  - Photograph album featuring Kichibei Murai's residences in Japan, circa 1899-1905 (Box 26)
    Cloth covers and accordion-style binding, measuring 6 1/4 x 8 1/4 inches and housing photographs of Murai's estate and interiors. There is some duplication between prints in this album and the other Murai albums.
  - Souvenir photograph album with images from Japan, circa 1899-1905 (Box 13)
    Bound album with dark lacquer covers measuring approximately 11 1/2 x 14 1/2 inches and containing large hand-tinted albumen photographs. Locales include Nikko and Hakone. The style and known negative numbers indicate that this album likely was created by the Kajima Sebei studio. A few images have been attributed by an expert to Kazuma Ogawa.
  - Souvenir photograph album with images from Japan, circa 1899-1905 (Box 14)
    Bound album with fine cloth covers, measuring approximately 11 x 14 inches and containing large hand-tinted albumen photographs. Includes images from Kyoto, Nikko, Tokyo, Nara, Nagasaki, and Saikio, often with English captions. From all indications this album likely was created by the Kajima Sebei studio, but there are also a few photographs attributed to other photographers such as Kazuma Ogawa, Kusakabei Kimbei, and Y. Isawa. There are also a number of untitled, unnumbered images.
  - Souvenir photograph album with images from Japan, 1899 (Box 15)
    Bound album with inlayed dark lacquer covers, measuring approximately 11.5 x 15.5 inches and larger than the other albums in this collection, containing about 60 large hand-colored albumen photographs mounted one to a page. The album spine is stamped, "Photographs, 1899." The larger inlay pieces are missing.
    As with other albums, there are traditional scenes of cherry blossoms, gardens, cultural sites, and landscapes. There are many portraits of Japanese men and women in traditional poses. Locales include Yokohama, Tokyo, Hakone, Fujiyama, Yamoto, and Kyoto. Includes many handwritten captions in English. Almost all the prints appear on commercial lists from Kusakabe Kimbei's studio.
  - Souvenir photograph album with images of Japanese culture, circa 1899-1905 (Box 16)
    Bound album with inlayed red lacquer covers measuring approximately 11 x 14 1/2 inches and containing large hand-tinted albumen photographs. The first photo is a large mounted black-and-white print of a party of men and women, with the Parrish family among them, taken at a well-known tourist location in front of a giant Buddha sculpture.
    As with other albums, scenes feature traditional Japanese souvenir images such as cherry blossoms, geishas, mountains, street scenes, and farmers. There are indications that this album may have been produced by the Farsari studio.
  - Volume in Japanese, including hand-colored illustrations, undated (Box 17)
    Cloth-covered accordian-style binding, measuring 7.5 x 10 inches. Appears to be an illustrated narrative.
  - Volume in Japanese, including hand-colored illustrations, undated (Box 18)
    Cloth-covered accordian-style binding, measuring 10 x 14.5 inches. Appears to be an illustrated narrative.
  - Souvenir photograph album with images from Japan, circa 1899-1905 (Box 19)
    Bound album with red lacquer covers that feature a framed, embedded photographic image of a sailboat on a mountain lake. The album measures approximately 11.5 x 15.5 inches and contains large hand-colored albumen photographs. In addition, the first photograph is a black-and-white personal souvenir print of a large party of foreigners, among them the Parrish family.
    Traditional scenes include gardens, cultural sites, landscapes, and portraits of Japanese in traditional poses, with English captions. There are indications that the photographs may be from the Farsari studio.
  - Souvenir photograph album with images from Japan, circa 1899-1905 (Box 20)
    Embroidered cloth-covered album bound accordion-style, measuring 11 x 14 inches and containing large albumen photographs, hand-colored and one black-and-white. It opens with street scenes taken in Osaka, and then moves to scenes of Kyoto's streets, landmark temples, and parks - all tourist destinations seen in other albums of its kind. Most of the photographs bear English captions.
    The style of the images seems to indicate the work of one photographer, with a few prints by others mixed in. One print, number 266, is attributed by an expert to noted photographer Kusakabe Kimbei, and several others closely resemble his style; however, it is uncertain if the entire album originated from his studio.
  - Souvenir photograph album with images from Japan, circa 1899-1905 (Box 23)
    Embroidered cloth-bound volume - with same fabric pattern as another album in the collection - measures approximately 11 1/2 x 14 1/4 inches, and contains large hand-tinted albumen photographs with traditional tourist trade subjects such as tea houses, geishas, flowers and gardens, and farmers.
    Many of the prints appear on Kajima Sebei's studio print lists. The source of the other images is uncertain, but there are a large number whose style resembles Kusakabe Kimbei's work. One print has been attributed to the amateur photographer Isawa.
  - Scrapbook album of family photographs taken in Japan and China, 1901-1903 (Box 21)
    Cloth-bound album (original embroidered cover removed; plain woven cover remains) measuring approximately 11.25 x 14.5 inches. The pages are mounted with small-format black-and-white snapshots and other family photographs; there are also two large prints of street scenes that may have been taken by the Parrish family and then enlarged and colorized by a Japanese studio. Many pages bear handwritten captions.
  - Rosa Parrish's postcard album (postcards have been removed and housed separately) (Box 30)
  - Rosa Parrish's postcards, 1890s-1900s (Box 31)